Guide to the Gilman Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gilman Family Papers
1659-1935
MS 240
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
Correspondence, diaries, writings, financial records, photographs, clippings, and other papers relating to the Gilman and Coit families of New England. The bulk of the collection relates to Edward Whiting Gilman (1823-1900), his family and his work as a clergyman and foreign secretary of the American Bible Society.
Gilman family
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Coit Family. III. Diaries, Writings, Financial and Personal Papers of Gilman Family Members. IV. Subject File.
Scope and Contents
The Gilman Family Papers consists of correspondence, diaries, writings, accountbooks, photographs, and newsclippings relating to the Gilman and Coit families, from the early eighteenth century to the first half of the twentieth century. In addition to the materials relating to the Gilman, Coit, and Bristol families, there are materials pertaining to some of the most prominent New England families, including the Trumbulls and Sillimans, with whom the Gilmans were related by marriage. There is also material pertaining to the history of Norwich, Connecticut. Most important is the correspondence and writings of Edward Whiting Gilman, brother of Daniel Coit Gilman (see Daniel Coit Gilman Collection, Yale University), who was a prominent clergyman in the Congregational Church and, from 1871 to 1900, the foreign secretary of the American Bible Society.
Edward Gilman of Norfolk, England, was the first of the Gilman family to emigrate to America, settling in Hingham, Massachusetts in 1638. Members of the family branched out through New England, settling in Exeter, New Hampshire and Norwich, Connecticut. William Charles Gilman moved to the latter town in 1816 and married Elizabeth Coit (1820), a descendant of one of the founders of Norwich. He became a partner in several business ventures, notably the Norwich Water Company, but due to the panic of 1837 suffered a series of financial reverses, causing him to move his family to New York City, where he died in 1844.
Edward Whiting Gilman, the oldest son of William Charles Gilman, was born in Norwich in 1823. He entered Yale College in 1839, and was graduated in 1843. In the autumn of that year he went to West Point, New York where he spent a year as an instructor in Professor Kinsley's school for boys. In November, 1844, he moved to New York City where he was engaged for several years as a teacher in private schools while attending lectures at Union Theological Seminary. In 1847 he accepted a tutorship at Yale College, a position he held for two years, while he attended lectures at the Seminary. In 1849 Gilman was ordained minister of the Congregational Church in Lockport, New York, serving from 1849 to 1856. This was followed by charges in Cambridge, Massachusetts (1856-1858), Bangor, Maine (1858-1863), and Stonington, Connecticut (1864-1871). In 1871 he accepted the position as foreign secretary of the American Bible Society where he remained until his death in 1900. In this capacity he made ex tensive trips to Europe and Mexico carrying on a lively correspondence with members of his family, especially his daughter, Caroline T. Gilman, pertaining to his experiences and observations.
The Gilman Family Papers are divided into four series: I. Correspondence; II. Coit Family; III. Diaries, Writings, Financial and Personal Papers of Gilman Family Members; and IV. Subject File.
CORRESPONDENCE, the greatest part of which is that of Edward Whiting Gilman, is arranged chronologically. It is preceded, however, by a selected list of important correspondents and includes a number of names prominent in nineteenth century education, politics, and religion. Among those listed are: Lyman Abbot, Leonard Bacon, Leonard Woolsey Bacon, James Bryce, Lewis Cass, Charles Anderson Dana, James Dwight Dana, Jeremiah Day, Timothy Dwight, John Charles Fremont, Arnold Guyot, Theodore T. Munger, James Ford Rhodes, Josiah Royce, William Henry Seward, Theodore Dwight Woolsey, and Benjamin Silliman, both father and son.
Series two, COIT FAMILY, consists of the papers of the Coit family and spans the years from 1659 to 1886. John Coit, the first member of the family to leave England for the colonies, arrived in Saybrook, Connecticut in 1630. In the course of the seventeenth century, members of the family settled in New London, Connecticut and finally in Norwich, Connecticut, where William Charles Gilman settled and married Elizabeth Coit on May 2, 1820. A majority of the series consists of correspondence, primarily that of Martha Coit to her mother, Mehetabel Chandler Coit, and to her sister, Elizabeth Gardiner. There is also considerable correspondence between Joshua Coit and his sister, Maria Coit Perit, and his father Daniel Lathrop Coit. A small group of diaries, biographical and genealogical materials, and memorabilia is filed at the end of the series.
Series III, DIARIES, WRITINGS, FINANCIAL AND PERSONAL PAPERS OF GILMAN FAMILY MEMBERS, consists primarily of personal and family materials, including diaries and account books, photos, scrapbooks, and memorabilia. There are, however, some writings, especially those of Edward Whiting Gilman, which relate to his studies at Yale College (1840-1843), his travels in Mexico (1878-1879), his travels in Europe (1880-1843), and a book he wrote while teaching in West Point, New York entitled, A Guide to West Point (1844). In addition, there are a number of articles written by Gilman while serving as foreign secretary of the American Bible Society from 1871 to 1900. The series also includes several diaries written by Gilman's daughter, Caroline, a journal containing family records (1874), and another on the family estate, "Coit Elms." Two journals kept by William Charles Gilman record his excursions in Pennsylvania in 1834 and the White Mountains in 1850. There is also a sketch of the Gilman family by Julia S. (Bristol) Gilman and a diary she kept while travelling in Europe in 1888 and again in 1926.
Series IV, SUBJECTS FILE, contains correspondence, photos, newsclippings, and an assortment of printed and manuscript materials pertaining to the following subjects:
Abbot Collegiate Association
Connecticut Indian Association
Bible Society
Boy's Meetings and Sabbath School
Congregational Church
Missionary Society
Norwich, Connecticut
Silliman Family
Trumbull Family
Biographical / Historical
Edward Whiting Gilman (1823-1900): in 1849 ordained a Congregational minister and served at the Congregational Church at Lockport, New York, from 1849-1856; later served in Cambridge, Mass., from 1856-1858, Bangor, Maine, from 1858-1863, and Stonington, Conn, from 1864-1871; secretary of the American Bible Society, 1871-1900.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Armed Forces; Education; Families; United States -- Description and travel; Connecticut; Europe -- Description and travel; Mexico -- Description and travel; Norwich (Conn.) -- History; Diaries; Clergy; Abbott, Lyman, 1835-1922; Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1830-1907; Bacon, Leonard, 1802-1881; Bristol, Julia Silliman Gilman, 1854-1943; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866; Coit, Daniel Lathrop, 1754-1833; Coit, Joshua, 1758-1798; Greene, Martha Coit Hubbard, 1706-1784; Coit, Mehetabel Chandler, 1673-1758; Dana, Charles A. (Charles Anderson), 1819-1897; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890; Gardiner, Elizabeth; Gilman, Arthur Frederick, 1801-1863; Gilman, Caroline Howard, 1794-1888; Gilman, Caroline T., 1794-1883; Gilman, Charles William, 1793-1870; Gilman, Daniel C. (Daniel Coit), 1831-1908; Gilman, Edward W. (Edward Whiting), 1823-1900; Gilman, Elizabeth Coit, 1796-1868; Gilman, Elizabeth Dwight Woolsey, ca. 1839-1910; Lane, Louisa Gilman, 1838-1922; Gilman, Maria Perit, 1824-1906; Gilman, Nathaniel, 1793-1858; Gilman, Rufus King, 1804-1828; Gilman, Serena, 1797-1881; Gilman, William C. (William Charles), 1795-1863; Gilman, William C. (William Charles), 1833-1922; Guyot, A. (Arnold), 1807-1884; Munger, Theodore Thornton, 1830-1910; Perit, Maria Coit, 1793-1885; Rhodes, James Ford, 1848-1927; Royce, Josiah, 1855-1916; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1801-1889; Bristol family; Coit family; Gilman family; Silliman family; Trumbull family; American Bible Society; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1729-(1845-1909) 1935, undated; Series I; 6' (16 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the Gilman family correspondence is arranged chronologically with the unidentified correspondence placed at the end of the series. There is, however, one box of selected letters which has been arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter.
  The number of items are contained in parentheses before the unit date.
  - Selected Alphabetical List
    - Abbot, Ezra (1), 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abbot, Lyman (1), 1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bacon, Leonard (3), 1854-1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bacon, Leonard Woolsey (2), [1833?], 1856 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bethune, George Washington (1), 1852 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bliss, Seth (1), 1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bryce, James (2), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cass, Lewis (1), 1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cattell, William C. (1), 1852 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cheever, George B. (7), 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dana, Charles Anderson (3), 1858 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dana, James Dwight (6), 1865, 1881,1884, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Day, Jeremiah (1), 1843 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Dexter, H.M. (2), 1856 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Dwight, Timothy (1), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Fremont, John Charles (1), 1850 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Guyot, Arnold Henry (1), 1854 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hawley, J.R. (1), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Howe, F.S. (copy) (1), 1853 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Huntington, William Reed (1), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - King, W.L. (1), 1853 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Munger, Theodore T. (2), 1857, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Perrin, H.H. (3), 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Quincy, John W. (1), 1853 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Rhodes, James Ford (1), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Royce, Josiah (3), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Rutherford, Ernest (1), (1905)? (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Seward, William Henry (1), 1850 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Sr. (4), 1844, 1847, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Sr. (20), 1853, 1855-1859 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Sr. (14), 1860, 1862-1864, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Jr. (4), 1851, 1878, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Sprague, William Buell (1), 1874 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Storrs, Richard Salter, Jr., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Trumbull, Jonathan (6), 1880, 1891, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Welman, A.R. (2), 1853 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Winthrop, Robert Charles (1), 1850 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Woolsey, Thedore Dwight (1), 1856 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gilman Family-Chronologically Arranged
    - 1729 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - 1788 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 1813 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - 1814 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 1815 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - 1816 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - 1818 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - 1819 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - 1820 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - 1821 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - 1822 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - 1823 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - 1824 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - 1825 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - 1826 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - 1827 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - 1828 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - 1829 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - 1830 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - 1831 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - 1832 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - 1833 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - 1834 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - 1835 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - 1836 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - 1837 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - 1838 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - 1839 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - 1840 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - 1841 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - 1842 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - 1843 January - June (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - 1843 July - December (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - 1844 January - August (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Gilman Family
    - 1844 September - December (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - 1845 January - July (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - 1845 August -December (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - 1846 January - December (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - 1847 March - November (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - 1848-1949 January - December (Box 3, Folder 78-79)
    - 1850 January - July (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - 1850 August - December (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - 1851-1854 January - December (Box 3, Folder 82-85)
    - 1855 January - November (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - 1856-1857 January - December (Box 3, Folder 87-88)
    - 1858 January - September (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - 1858 October - December (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - 1859 January - July (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - 1859 August - December (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - 1860 January - July (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - 1860 August - December (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - 1861January - July (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - 1861August - December (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - 1862 January - May (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - 1862 June - August (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - 1862 September - December (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - 1863 January - May (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - 1863 June - July (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - 1863 August - December (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - 1864-1866 January - December (Box 5, Folder 103-105)
    - 1867 January - September (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - 1867 October - December (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - 1868 January - May (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - 1868 June - December (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - 1869 January - July (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - 1869 August - December (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - 1870 January - July (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - 1870 August - December (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - 1871 March - June (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - 1871 July - December (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - 1872 January - July (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - 1872 August - December (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - 1873 January - July (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - 1873 August - December (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - 1874-1875 January - December (Box 7, Folder 120-121)
    - 1876 January - August (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - 1876 September - December (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - 1877 January - August (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - 1877 September - December (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - 1878 January - July (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - 1878 August - December (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - 1879 January - July (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - 1879 August - September (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - 1879 October (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - 1879 November - December (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - 1880 January - July (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - 1880 August - December (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - 1881 January - November (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - 1882 January - April (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - 1882 May (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - 1882 June - July (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - 1882 August - December (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - 1883 January - May (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - 1883 June - August (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - 1883 September - December (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - 1884-1885 January - December (Box 8, Folder 142-143)
    - 1886 January - May (Box 9, Folder 144)
    - 1886 June - December (Box 9, Folder 145)
    - 1887 January - May (Box 9, Folder 146)
    - 1887 June - December (Box 9, Folder 147)
    - 1888 January - May (Box 9, Folder 148)
    - 1888 June (Box 9, Folder 149)
    - 1888 July (Box 9, Folder 150)
    - 1888 August - September (Box 9, Folder 151)
    - 1889 January - June (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - 1889 July - December (Box 9, Folder 153)
    - 1890 January - July (Box 9, Folder 154)
    - 1890 August - December (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - 1891 January - June (Box 10, Folder 156)
    - 1891 July - August (Box 10, Folder 157)
    - 1891 September - December (Box 10, Folder 158)
    - 1892 January - June (Box 10, Folder 159)
    - 1892 July - December (Box 10, Folder 160)
    - 1893 January - August (Box 10, Folder 161)
    - 1893 September - December (Box 10, Folder 162)
    - 1894 January - April (Box 10, Folder 163)
    - 1894 May - December (Box 10, Folder 164)
    - 1895 January - August (Box 10, Folder 165)
    - 1895 September - December (Box 10, Folder 166)
    - 1896 January - March (Box 11, Folder 167)
    - 1896 April - May (Box 11, Folder 168)
    - 1896 June - December (Box 11, Folder 169)
    - 1897 January - April (Box 11, Folder 170)
    - 1897 May - August (Box 11, Folder 171)
    - 1897 September - December (Box 11, Folder 172)
    - 1898 January - May (Box 11, Folder 173)
    - 1898 June - August (Box 11, Folder 174)
    - 1898 September - December (Box 11, Folder 175)
    - 1899 January - July (Box 11, Folder 176)
    - 1899 August - December (Box 11, Folder 177)
    - 1900 January - May (Box 11, Folder 178)
    - 1900 June - August (Box 11, Folder 179)
    - 1900 September - December 6 (Box 12, Folder 180)
    - 1900 December 7-31 (Box 12, Folder 181)
    - 1901 January - February (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - 1901 March - December (Box 12, Folder 183)
    - 1902-1903 January - December (Box 12, Folder 184-185)
    - 1904 January - October (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - 1904 November - December (Box 12, Folder 187)
    - 1905 January - September (Box 12, Folder 188)
    - 1905 October - December (Box 12, Folder 189)
    - 1906 January - March (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - 1906 April - May (Box 13, Folder 191)
    - 1906 June - December (Box 13, Folder 192)
    - 1907 January - March (Box 13, Folder 193)
    - 1907 April - December (Box 13, Folder 194)
    - 1908 January - December (Box 13, Folder 195)
    - 1909 January (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - 1909 February - April (Box 13, Folder 197)
    - 1909 May - August (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - 1909 September - December (Box 13, Folder 199)
    - 1910 January - May (Box 14, Folder 200)
    - 1910 July - December (Box 14, Folder 201)
    - 1911-1913 January - December (Box 14, Folder 202-204)
    - 1914 January - June (Box 14, Folder 205)
    - 1914 July - December (Box 14, Folder 206)
    - 1915 March - December (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - 1916 January - August (Box 14, Folder 208)
    - 1916 September - December (Box 14, Folder 209)
    - 1917 January - March (Box 14, Folder 210)
    - 1917 April - May (Box 14, Folder 211)
    - 1918 January - June (Box 15, Folder 212)
    - 1918 July - October (Box 15, Folder 213)
    - 1919 April - December (Box 15, Folder 214)
    - 1920 January - September (Box 15, Folder 215)
    - 1921 January - December (Box 15, Folder 216)
    - 1922 January - August (Box 15, Folder 217)
    - 1922 September 1-8 (Box 15, Folder 218)
    - 1922 September 9-30 (Box 15, Folder 219)
    - 1922 October - December (Box 15, Folder 220)
    - 1923-1924 January - December (Box 15, Folder 221-222)
    - 1925 January - November (Box 15, Folder 223)
    - 1926 January - May (Box 15, Folder 224)
    - 1927, 1929-1930, 1935 (Box 15, Folder 225-228)
    - undated (Box 16, Folder 229-232)
- Coit Family, 1659-(1764-1774, 1824-1837) 1895; Series II; 1' (3 boxes)
  The COIT FAMILY series consists primarily of correspondence which is arranged chronologically followed by a small group of diaries, genealogical materials, and family memorabilia.
  - Correspondence
    - List for letters from 1673-1778 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - 1659, 1988, 1696, 1698-1699 (Box 17, Folder 2-6)
    - 1703, 1705, 1723, 1724, 1724-1725 (Box 17, Folder 7-11)
    - 1726, 1727, 1728, 1731, 1743 (Box 17, Folder 12-16)
    - 1745, 1751, 1754, 1758, 1760 (Box 17, Folder 17-21)
    - 1764, 1765, 1766, 1767, 1774, 1778 (Box 17, Folder 22-27)
    - 1783, 1784, 1789, 1790, 1795 (Box 17, Folder 28-32)
    - 1798, 1800, 1801, 1803, 1804 (Box 17, Folder 33-37)
    - 1805, 1806, 1807, 1808, 1810 (Box 17, Folder 38-42)
    - 1812, 1814, 1815, 1817, 1818 (Box 17, Folder 43-47)
    - 1819, 1820, 1821, 1822, 1823 (Box 17, Folder 48-52)
    - 1824, 1825, 1826, 1828, 1829, 1830 (Box 17, Folder 53-58)
    - 1831, 1832, 1833, 1835, 1836 (Box 18, Folder 59-63)
    - 1837, 1838, 1839, 1840, 1841 (Box 18, Folder 64-68)
    - 1844, 1845, 1850, 1853, 1858 (Box 18, Folder 69-73)
    - 1859, 1860, 1861, 1862, 1864 (Box 18, Folder 74-78)
    - 1865, 1873, 1874, 1876, 1877 (Box 18, Folder 79-83)
    - 1877, 1882, 1886 (Box 18, Folder 84-86)
    - Biographical Sketches of Daniel Lathrop Coit and Daniel Wadaworth Coit, 1860, 1877 (Box 19, Folder 87)
    - "A Brief Exposition on the 45th Psalm" written for Faith (Trumbull) Wadsworth, 1793 (Box 19, Folder 88)
    - Coit family genealogy (Box 19, Folder 89)
    - Diaries of Maria Coit Perit, 1836-1837 (Box 19, Folder 90)
    - Journal of John Backus, 1762 (Box 19, Folder 91)
    - "Martha, daughter of Mehetabel Chandler Coit", 1895 (Box 19, Folder 92)
    - "A Meditation or Poem…" on the "First forty years of his life" [Joseph Coit?], undated (Box 19, Folder 93)
    - Miscellaneous clippings and photos (Box 19, Folder 94)
- Diaries, Writings, Financial and Personal Papers of Gilman Family Members, 1818-(1850-1900) 1932; Series III; 5' (12 boxes)
  This series contains the diaries, writings, account books and financial records, genealogical materials, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia of a dozen Gilman family members. The series is divided into two subsections: "Gilman Family, General," and "Gilman Family, Individual Members."
  "Gilman Family, General" contains genealogical materials about Gilman and related families, photos, account books and financial papers, scrapbooks, and memorabilia which cannot be attributed to an individual family member. This section is arranged alphabetically by title or subject category.
  "Gilman Family, Individual Members" is arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual family member. Materials are filed under a given family member's name in the following order: diaries and calendar books, journals and memoirs; personal finances and account books; genealogical material; writings, both manuscript and printed, including articles, essays, books speeches, and sermons; miscellaneous notes; newspaper clippings and printed matter; and memorabilia, including scrapbooks and photos. It should be noted, however, that not all family members will have materials in each of these categories.
  - Gilman family, General
    - Account and stocks, 1871-1914 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Annotated calendars, 1892, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Articles, sermons, and circulars, 1860, 1863, 1896-1897, 1910, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Biographical sketch of Baroness Burdett Coutts, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Diaries and journals, 1818, 1822, 1826, 1862 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Genealogical materials, undated (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
    - Gilman family genealogy, 1888, 1896 (Box 20, Folder 8-9)
    - Gilman family genealogy.
      General
      See: box 34 See: box 35
    - Household accounts, unidentified, 1867-1900 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Memorabilia and personal documents, 1859, 1878, 1880-1881, 1889 1891, 1907-1908, 1913 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Notes and clippings on beekeeping, 1853 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Old Families of Norwich Connecticut, 1600-1800, by Mary E. Perkins (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Photo
      See: box 34
    - Photos (Box 21, Folder 17-19)
    - Photos of family handicrafts (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Poems and literary fragments, unidentified, undated (Box 21, Folder 21)
    - Reminiscences of Rev. George B. Cheever, undated (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Scrapbook, programs and reviews of concerts and operas, 1882-1900 (Box 22, Folder 23-24)
    - Miscellaneous tributes and memorials, 1876, 1896, 1898 (Box 22, Folder 25)